Pluto
Gamilas Pluto Forward Base
The Teron ship made a hyperspace jump?
And they destroyed the resupply base? Have you gone mad?
But, Commander Goer... It's clear they broke the light-speed barrier?
Silence!
Do you really think a commander in charge of a galactic theater,
can report such nonsense to imperial command?
Shultz!
I shall only be able to report to our lord after you've provided a proper report.
（ナレーション）＜西暦２１９９年＞
＜地球は
ガミラスとの戦いに敗れ→
人類滅亡まで
あと１年と迫っていた＞
＜国連宇宙軍は　ひそかに
恒星間宇宙船　ヤマトを開発＞
＜大マゼラン銀河にある惑星
イスカンダルに→
地球環境の再生システムを
受け取りに行くのである＞
＜宇宙戦艦ヤマトは　ついに→
１６万８０００光年の
大航海へと旅立った＞
（ゲール・通信）テロンの艦が
超空間ジャンプした!?→
補給基地を失ったうえに
なんの寝言だ！
（シュルツ）しかし　ゲール司令→
ヤツらが
光速突破したのは　紛れもない…。
（ゲール）
黙れ！　銀河方面軍を預かる身で→
そんな夢物語を　帝星司令部に→
報告できると思うか!?
んん…。
（ゲール・通信）シュルツ！
貴様が　正しい報告をして→
初めて　私は
総統に　ご報告できるのだ。
んん…。
言ってる意味は分かるな？
You understand what I'm asking, yes?
Yes, sir.
（シュルツ）はっ。
（ゲール）そうすれば　貴様たちを→
If so, I'll speak to command about promoting all of you
２等臣民から
１等ガミラスへ引き上げるよう→
私が　上へ進言してやろう。
from second-class Gamilans to first-class.
いいか？
正しい報告だぞ　シュルツ！
Got it? I want a proper report, Shultz!
He doesn't understand anything...
何も分かっておらん。
（ガンツ）はっ？
Show me the Zupist footage.
（シュルツ）ズピストの映像を出せ。
（シュルツ）問題は　これだ。
Here's the issue. What could have done this?
どうしたら
こんなことができる？→
何を使ったら
こんなまねができるのだ。
What could even make something like this possible?
The flight plan the UN's Yamato Plan HQ made does not allow for any lost time at Pluto.
（真田）国連ヤマト計画本部が
立てた　航海日程には→
冥王星での日数のロスは
含まれていません。→
つまり　メ２号作戦の発令は→
In other words, any decision about carrying out Operation M-2 has been left to us.
我々の判断に
委ねられているわけです。
We should do it!
（古代進）
やるべきですよ！　後顧の憂いを→
We should disable the Pluto base, if only to prevent any troubles with it later.
断つという意味でも
冥王星は　たたくべきです。
Operation M-2
Navigation Officer, your opinion?
（沖田十三）航海長　意見は？
（島）
航海科としては　このコースで→
I believe this to be our fastest course out of the solar system.
太陽系を
突破するのが最短だと考えます。→
つまり…。
待ってくれ。　このコースだと→
Meaning that...
Wait... Following that course, we'll pass Pluto without mounting any attack.
冥王星をたたかずに
行き過ぎることになるぞ。
I understand how you feel. However, our flight plan has no leeway.
気持ちは分かるが　現実問題として
日程に余裕はないんだ。
But...
しかし…。
（相原・通信）第一艦橋より　報告。→
Report from the main bridge. We've picked up a distress call.
救難信号を　捉えました。→
国連宇宙軍　標準コード。
出力　微弱。
UN Cosmo Force Standard Code. Very weak.
What's the ship's name?
（通信）艦名は？
（相原）特定できません。
We can't tell. It's coming from
発信地点は　土星の衛星→
the vicinity of the south pole of Enceladus, one of Saturn's moons.
エンケラドゥス南極付近。
Saturn, huh? The opposite direction from Pluto.
（太田）土星か。
冥王星とは　反対方向ですね。
そっちで作ったコースからもな。
ははっ…。
And from the course you plotted, too.
エンケラドゥスに上陸した場合
日程のロスは？
Assuming we go to Enceladus, how many days are lost?
２日の損失です。
戦術長　意見具申します。
Two.
Here is my opinion, as the Tactical Officer:
ここで　貴重な日数を
失うべきではないと思います。
We shouldn't lose time here.
（島）
何を言うんだ　古代！　船乗りが→
What are you talking about, Kodai? A sailor can't abandon another sailor!
船乗りを　見捨てるっていうのか!?
いるかどうかも分からない→
Since we're unsure there even are survivors, we shouldn't squander valuable time!
生存者のために　貴重な時間を
浪費すべきじゃない！
それは　さっき
お前が言ってたことじゃないか！
Is that not what you just said?
んん…。
（森雪）はぁ…。
Right now, our priority...
我々が　今すべきことは…。
（島）イスカンダルへ行くことだ。→
...is to reach Iscandar. Not to destroy the Pluto base.
冥王星を　たたくことじゃない。
たとえ
生存者がいる確率が低くても→
Even if the chance of survivors is minuscule, we should go.
救助には　行くべきです。
ううむ…。
あっ！
うわぁ～！
（南部）なんだ!?
機関部　状況を報告せよ。
What?
Engine room, status report.
（徳川）いかんな。
コンデンサーの　一部が→
This is bad... Part of the condenser is on the verge of melting.
溶けかかっとる。
（山崎）安全弁は　閉じたな？
We closed the safety valve, right?
（薮）はい。
（徳川）おそらく　波動砲を→
Probably from firing the Wave Motion Gun.
ぶっ放した影響じゃろう。
If we do nothing, it could paralyze the ship.
（徳川）このまま放置すると
航行不能に陥るかもしれん。
（真田・通信）復旧のめどは？
How long will repairs take?
That isn't an easy question. To repair it, we'd need to...
やっかいじゃな。
何しろ　こいつを修理するには…。
ジューー
（２人）うわっ！
Cosmonite 90?
コスモナイト９０？
（真田）コンデンサーの修理に
不可欠な　希少鉱物だよ。
It's a rare material required to repair the condenser.
Hirata, do we have any on board?
平田君　備蓄の方は？
（平田）修理に必要な十分量には→
Not nearly enough for the repairs.
とても…。
（新見）あった。　ありました。
There! I found it.
Enceladus has an abandoned cosmonite mine. We can resupply there.
ちょうど　このエンケラドゥスに
コスモナイトの採掘場が→
放棄されたままになっており
補給が可能です。
Change course. Head for Enceladus.
針路変更。　本艦は　これより
エンケラドゥスに向かう。
However, recovering the cosmonite is our priority. Understood?
ただし
コスモナイトの確保が優先だ。
分かっているな？
（２人）はい！
Yes, sir.
（シュルツ）
テロンの艦が　針路を変えた？
The Teron ship has changed course?
Our recon ships show them heading toward the sixth planet, Zedan.
（ガンツ）
偵察機の報告では　第６惑星→
ゼダンへ向かっているもようです。
Jarletora, wasn't a recon landing ship stationed near Zedan?
ヤレトラー
ゼダン付近には　偵察揚陸艦が→
１隻　配備してあったな？
（ヤレトラー）はっ。
Yes.
Use that. Take prisoners if possible.
それを使え。
できれば　捕虜を取るのだ。
I want to know what they're up to.
ヤツらの意図が知りたい。
The OMCS is amazing. It can make as much of this food as you want.
（太田）
ＯＭＣＳって　すげぇよな。→
こんな食べ物を
無尽蔵に作っちゃうんだぜ。
But what does it use for raw material?
（相原）でも　原料は何なんだろう？
（太田）ははっ…
難しいこと聞くなよ　相原ちゃん。
Don't ask hard questions, Aihara.
ん？　あれ？
真田さんは　そんなもんだけで→
Huh? That's all you want, Sanada?
平気なんですか？
（真田）ああ。→
Yeah. Consuming unnecessary calories is foolish.
無駄なカロリー摂取は
愚かな行為だからね。
んん…。
あの…　真田さん→
Um, Sanada, what does the OMCS use to make the food?
ＯＭＣＳが作る食べ物って
何から作られてるんですか？
はっ…　知らない方が
幸せだと思うよ。　ん？
I think you're better off not knowing.
隣　空いてるか？
ん？
May I sit here?
Sure.
かまわないよ。
ふっ。
I'm not against the rescue operation itself. Just...
俺は　救難活動そのものに→
反対したんじゃないんだ。　ただ…。
You lost your brother on Pluto. I understand your desire to redress that.
兄さんを
冥王星で　亡くしてるんだもんな。
あそこを
たたきたい気持ちは分かるよ。
俺だって　本当は…。
んん…。
Actually, I'm the same way...
My dad was a sailor. And he always used to say...
俺のおやじさ　船乗りだったんだ。
そのおやじが　よく言ってたのさ。
Listen, Daisuke.
（大吾・回想）((いいか？　大介。
父さんたちは　何があっても→
Sailors like your dad never abandon their comrades, no matter what.
仲間を見捨てたりはしない。→
That's what it means to be a sailor... A true sailor.
それが　船乗りだ。
本当の船乗りなんだ))
I wanted to be like him. That's why I became a sailor.
（島）俺は　そんなおやじのように
なりたくて→
船乗りを目指したんだ。
They're such good friends.
（星名）
仲がいいんだなぁ　あの二人。→
Both were promoted because those who would have had their jobs got killed.
二人とも
出港前に　責任者が戦死して→
大抜擢されたんだって。
（百合亜）たなぼたじゃない。
（星名）男の友情だよ。
Aren't they lucky?
It's a friendship between men.
じゃなくって！
単純なだけ。
No, I mean...
They're just simple.
（星名・百合亜）えっ？
They're just self-absorbed. You shouldn't try to emulate them.
自己陶酔型っていうやつね。
見習っちゃダメよ。
あっ　ははっ…。
はい　そうします！
Right! Understood!
After inspection, team 5 is to gather in the briefing room.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）第五分隊は　点検終了後
ブリーフィングルームに集合。→
繰り返す。
第五分隊は　点検終了後→
Repeat
After inspection, team 5 is to gather in the briefing room.
ブリーフィングルームに集合。
今後の機体整備→
We will discuss our maintenance and operation plans.
運用について　打ち合わせる。
Inertial control isn't on in here, right?
（玲）ここは
慣性制御が　働いてないんですね。
（加藤）こんだけ積み込むんだ。
There's so much stuff in here... We're better off without gravity.
重力は　ない方がいいのさ。→
で　なんだ？
申請があった→
So, what is it?
Permission was granted for the extra ammunition you requested.
予備弾倉　増加の件→
許可が下りました。
ありがたい。
Thanks.
どうだ？　主計科の方は。
How's the accounting going?
はい…　楽しくやってます。
Fine. I'm enjoying it.
（ガミロイド　ガミラス語で）
Target approaching orbit of the eighth satellite.
Command priority: capture of crew.
Weapons use permitted, as necessary.
（太田）なんか
ひび割れた鏡餅みたいだなぁ。
It looks like a messed-up golf ball.
あの氷の表面に出来た亀裂から→
On that frozen surface, we've seen geysers
土星や
ほかの衛星の潮汐力の影響で→
caused by the tidal pull from Saturn and other planets.
間欠泉のような水の噴出が
確認されているんだよ。
エンケラドゥスに上陸する。
Landing on Enceladus.
Begin descent.
降下　始め。
（島）進入角よし。→
Approach angle is fine. Forward at minimum speed.
両舷　前進微速。
赤１５　下げ舵１６。
Red 15, descent angle 16.
Lower bow, and prepare for docking.
艦首　やや下げ。　接岸準備。
（太田）準備よし。
All ready.
XO Sanada, you're in charge of the mining site.
真田副長は
採掘現場で　作業の指揮を執れ。
はい。
森船務長→
Yes, sir.
Operations Officer Mori.
Take Analyzer and a medical team to the distress signal's source.
君は　アナライザーを連れ
医療班とともに　発信源に急行。
See if there is anyone you can help.
救難活動に当たれ。
Yes, sir.
はい。
古代　お前は　森君のエスコートだ。
Kodai, you are to escort Mori.
あっ。
あの～　それは　どういう…。
Um, what do you mean?
（ＡＵ０９）護衛任務ノ
コトト　思ワレマス。
I believe you are to protect her.
いえ　必要ありません。
No, that won't be necessary.
（榎本・鼻歌「銀河航路」）
♪♪　たら～ら　ら～ららら
（榎本）♪♪　ら～ららら　ららら
What a treasure trove...
（榎本）こいつぁ　宝の山ですな。
（真田）作業を急がせてくれ→
Boatswain, complete the work as fast as you can.
掌帆長！
（榎本）アイアイサー！→
Aye aye, sir.
そういや　古代のヤツは　姫の→
So I guess Kodai's off to escort the princess.
お供らしいですな。
（真田）ん？
In training school, I was his instructor.
（榎本）いえね
訓練学校で　あいつらの→
指導教官を　やってたんですよ。
女の扱いが
下手なヤツでしたからねぇ。→
He never did know how to deal with women.
ははっ　大丈夫ですかなぁ？
I wonder if he'll be all right...
Two girls and a robot alone?
大丈夫なわけないだろ
女の子とロボットだけなんてさ。
Don't worry.
ご心配なく。
あなたの手は　煩わせません。
You won't need to do a thing.
私ハ優秀。　任セテ安心。
そりゃ　どうも。
I am quite capable. You may leave it to me.
Glad to hear it.
≪まったく　心強いね。
≪護衛は任せますが→
Glad to hear it indeed.
I'll leave the escort to you. But on the ground, you obey my orders.
現場では　こちらの指示に
従ってもらいます。
Right, right.
はい　はい。
One "right" is enough.
「はい」は　１回で結構です。
んん…。
Right, right.
はいはい。
あなたねぇ…。
Hey...
（真琴）ねえねえ
あの二人　怪しくない？
Hey, aren't those two kind of suspicious together?
I detect no suspicious activity.
不審ナ行動ハ
確認サレマセン。
んん…　あんたって　つまんない。
You're such a bore.
それにしても　この救難信号→
But this distress signal... Who could have sent it?
一体　誰が出してるんだろ？
What?
何？
変なこと…　聞いていいかな？
Could I ask a strange question?
I guess...
いいけど…。
おおっ！　直感　的中。
I was right!
君　宇宙人に　親戚とかいる？
Are you related to any aliens?
はい？
（真琴）ううっ！
Am I what?
No, never mind. Forget it.
いや　いい。　忘れて。
Now approaching signal source.
間モナク　発信地点　上空デス。
あははっ…。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウゥーー！（警告音）
間違いない。　地球の艦ね。
This is definitely an Earth ship.
このシルエットから見て
おそらく…。
With that conning tower, it's probably...
磯風型　突撃宇宙駆逐艦。
An Isokaze-class assault destroyer.
The same type as the Yukikaze.
ユキカゼの同型艦だ。
It's frozen over, so I can't read the ship's name.
凍ってて　艦名は読めないか。
（真琴）森さ～ん！　古代さ～ん！→
Mori! Kodai!
We can enter over here!
こっから入れそうですよ。
ピィーー
ピッ　ピッ　ピッ　ピッ　ピッ…
これだけが
生きて　信号を送っていたのね。
This is the only system still working. It's transmitting the distress call.
ピッ　ピッ　ピッ　ピッ…
ああ…。
Yeah.
I'll look around a little more.
もう少し　調べてみる。
じゃあ→
Okay, I'll find the ship's log.
僕は　航海日誌を。
うん　お願い。
Okay, thanks.
It's no good...
ダメだ…。
≪ドォーン！
んんっ！　ガミラスだ！
えっ？
Gamilans!
They got the seagull!
シーガルがやられた。
（真琴）何かあったんですか？
Did something happen?
ピシュン！
ドドォーン！
（真琴）うわっ！　わっ…。
君は　ヤマトへ救援要請。
分かった。
You request help from the Yamato.
Understood.
≪ドン　ドン　ドン（ドアをたたく音）
原田君！
Harada!
I'm locked in!
≪（真琴）
閉じ込められちゃいました！
くぅ～…　この～！　ううっ！
Open, damn you!
This is the medical team. Yamato, please respond.
≪こちらメディック…。
ダメだ！
No good.
Analyzer, weren't you going to help?
アナライザー！
役に立つんじゃなかったのか!?
We are currently under Gamilas attack.
現在　ガミラスから
攻撃を受けています。
We require immediate assistance!
至急　救援　願います。
（相原・通信）こちらヤマト。　本艦も
現在　敵機甲部隊の攻撃を受け→
This is the Yamato!
We are currently under attack by enemy armored units.
これと交戦中！
えっ!?
ドカン　ドカン！
ドォーン！
（太田）右舷に被弾！　損害軽微！
Hit to starboard! Damage minimal!
（南部）機関停止中のため
主砲　副砲とも　使用不能。
Engine is off line, so both main and secondary guns are dead.
Okay, that's our cue!
（隊員）よっしゃ　出番だ！
（隊員）待ってろ　ガミ公！
Fighters are to launch and engage the enemy.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（百合亜）
敵地上部隊の掃討に当たれ。→
Repeat, fighters are to launch...
繰り返す。　航空隊は…。
Withdraw! Withdraw immediately!
≫退避～！　退避　急げ～！
ドカン！
バッカ野郎！
Idiots!
（榎本）よっと。
ヤマトを攻撃するには→
They don't nearly have the forces to attack the Yamato.
戦力が少ない。
ですな。
Yup.
≪いいぞ。　その調子だ。
Okay, just like that.
（真琴）へえ　あんた　役に立つんだ。
当然デス。
So you're useful, after all.
Of course.
妙だな…　攻撃がやんだ。
≪古代君→
This is strange.
They've stopped attacking.
Kodai, the Yamato is also under fire!
≪ヤマトも攻撃を受けてるみたい。
はっ！
ピシュン　ピシュン！
ドカン　ドカン！　ドォーン！
We can't launch?
（加藤）出せない!?
（整備員）採掘班を→
We're still recovering the dig team!
収容中なんです。
ここから出すには→
If you want to launch from here, we'll need to gain altitude.
もっと高度を取らなきゃ
無理なんですよ。
（篠原）おいおい　それじゃあ
俺たちゃ　どうすりゃいいわけ？
Hold on... Then what should we do?
I guess we'll borrow it.
（加藤）あれを拝借するか。
（篠原）ん？　あれ？
"It"?
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウー　ウウー（警報）
ピッ
ん？　ちょっと！
Hey!
発艦命令　下りたのかよ!?
（加藤）おい　誰が乗ってる!?
Did they issue launch orders?
Hey, who's in that thing?
（整備員）
航空隊の人じゃないんですか？
It isn't one of the pilots?
（加藤）ん？
（篠原）んん～？
ピシュン！
ドオォーーン！
ガン！　ガン！
ピピピピッ…　ピピッ
バシュン！
ドオォーーン！
ピシュ　ピシュ　ピシュ　ピシュ…
ガン！
ドオォーーン！
（加藤・通信）
おい　そこの！　官姓名を名乗れ！
Hey! You there! State your name and rank!
ピシュー　ピシュー！　ピシュー！
I don't know who you are, but go assist the medical team!
（加藤）誰だか知らんが
貴様は　メディックの救援に回れ！
こちらメディック。
ヤマト　応答　願います。
This is the medical team. Yamato, please respond!
（通信）メディック　聞こえるか？→
Medical team, do you copy?
On my way now.
現在　そちらへ急行している。
よし。
（真琴）やった～！
Okay!
You did it!
≪きゃあ～！
はっ！
Mori!
森君…。
バババババッ！
（ガミラス語で）
Take her to the tank.
古代さん！
顔を出すな！
Kodai!
Stay down!
バババババッ…
うっ！
ううっ…　くっ！
あっ！
パシュ！
くっ！
あっ　救急箱！
The first aid box!
敵デスヨ。
関係ない！
That's an enemy.
It doesn't matter!
あっ！
（加藤）くらえ　ガミ公！
バシュン！　バシュン！
Take this, Gammy!
ガン！
ドオォーン！
バババババッ！
ピュン！
パシュ！
んんっ！
Darn!
くそっ！
んっ…。
ドカッ！
ガッ！
んんっ！　うっ…。
パシュ！
ピュン　ピュン！
Kodai!
古代君！
逃げろ！
Run!
えっ？　うわっ！
ダダダダダッ！
あっ　伏せろ！
はっ！
Get down!
バシュン！
ドオォーーン！
Pretty impressive.
いい腕してるぜ。
うん。
Yeah.
あっ…　ああっ！
えっ？
あ…　ありがとう。
おかげで助かった。
Thank you. You saved me.
ああ。　俺は　こいつに助けられた。
This thing saved me.
えっ？
ん？
あっ！
どうしたの？
What's wrong?
Hey! What's wrong?
ねえ　どうしたの!?
ピュン！　ピュン　ピュン　ピュン…
あっ　あぁ…。
これは　兄さんのだ…。
This was my brother's...
Mamoru            Kodai
This ship was my brother's ship!
この艦は　兄さんの艦だった。
It was my brother's Yukikaze!
兄さんのユキカゼだったんだ！
Yukikaze
Remove your helmet.
（加藤）ヘルメットを取れ。
（篠原）おお～。
（加藤）ったく…→
Jeez... I should have known.
お前ってヤツは。
Huh?
あら？　戦術長は？
（島）古代なら→
Where's the tactical officer?
Kodai is giving his report.
報告に行ってる。　君はいいの？
You don't need to go?
報告します。　救難信号は→
Reporting.
Origin of distress call was the destroyer Yukikaze, of the UN Cosmo Force First Fleet.
国連宇宙軍　第一艦隊所属→
駆逐艦　ユキカゼのものと確認。
There were no survivors on board...
ユキカゼに…
生存者は　ありませんでした。
生存者は　なしか…。
No survivors, huh?
古代。
あっ。
Kodai.
地球を　ユキカゼのように
したくはないな。
We don't want the Earth to end up like the Yukikaze, do we?
はい。
No, we don't.
Here lie the twenty-four brave souls who crewed the Yukikaze. May they rest in peace.
Episode 4:
Gravestone on a Frozen Field
The planet with the king of the dead's name stands before the Yamato.
Unless the planet is overcome, humanity has no future.
All crew, battle stations! Our target is Pluto!
Can the Yamato break through the trap that lies in wait?
The biggest battle of the solar system begins now.
Next time: The Trap on All Sides.
There are 362 days left before humanity is extinct.
６１年前の今日、日本が独立を回
復したことを受け、
政府は、主権回復の日の式典を
東京で開いた。
一方、その後も長く
アメリカの施政権下に置かれた沖
縄では、